"How Well Do GLP-1 Drugs Like Ozempic
(Semaglutide) Work for Weight Loss?"
Older weight-loss
medications achieve
approximately 5 percent
reduction in body weight
over placebo,
whereas these new GLP-1
agonists, like Ozempic,
produce about triple the effect,
about 15 percent.
But what does that mean in terms
of numbers on the scale?
In an analysis of more than
100 clinical trials
of earlier anti-obesity
medications,
in studies lasting
up to 76 weeks,
drug-induced weight loss
never exceeded
more than 9 pounds (4 kg).
If you put all the GLP-1 drug
trials together,
over an average of about a year,
they led to about 19 pounds
(8 kg) of weight loss.
And that folded in
some of the older GLP-1 drugs,
like liraglutide,
that don’t work as well.
If you just look at semaglutide,
the high-dose Ozempic
sold as Wegovy for weight loss,
we’re looking at more like
27 pounds (12 kg) lost,
which translates into about
three and a half inches (9 cm)
off the waist.
Which GLP-1 drug works best?
An oral version of Ozempic
has been developed.
Though it hasn’t been approved
for weight loss,
preliminary evidence suggests
it causes similar weight loss
to the injectable version.
The latest GLP-1 drug approved
for weight loss, tirzepatide,
sold as Zepbound,
appears to beat out semaglutide,
with nearly 19 percent
of body weight lost,
over 40 pounds (18 kg),
with more like five and a half
inches (14 cm) off the waist.
How does that compare
to bariatric surgery?
It’s actually not that far off
from long-term
surgical weight loss.
Now, remember,
these are averages.
Bariatric surgery
doesn’t always work.
The failure rate
for the gold standard procedure
is approximately 20 percent,
but not everyone responds
to the GLP-1 drugs either.
In the big Ozempic trials,
about a third of people were
"super responders,"
but as many as one in six didn’t
lose significant weight at all,
even after taking the drug
for more than a year.
So, despite impressive results
at a population level,
up to 20 percent of patients
fail to achieve
significant weight loss
with either surgical
or drug-based approaches.
Here’s the longest trial
to date,
four years of high-dose Ozempic
for weight loss.
Here’s how the spread looked
at the end of Year Two,
with each of the thousands
of participants lined up
from those losing
the most weight
to the those losing the least.
The average weight loss was
about 10 percent;
so, some lost even more weight,
and sometimes,
a lot more weight,
some lost less,
and some even gained weight,
as much as maybe 40 pounds
(18 kg),
even after continuing
to inject the drug for years.
Here’s the average
weight-loss curve
of those getting high-dose
Ozempic for four years,
versus those getting
placebo injections,
for an overall weight loss
over placebo of about 9 percent.
OK, but the most striking thing
about this graph is the plateau.
They were being injected with
the drug the whole four years,
but weight loss stalled
after only about a year.
This happened in study after
study after study after study,
with both Ozempic
and the newer tirzepatide.
So, even under
the best of circumstances,
with the most potent GLP-1 drugs
taken at the highest
allowable dose
for at least a year
to obtain the full weight loss,
we’re only looking at
a 34-pound (15 kg) drop
before the weight loss stops.
So, if you look at all three
of the original
placebo-controlled
Ozempic weight loss trials,
the participants
started out obese,
and after more than a year
on the drug
(when it effectively
stopped working),
they were still obese.
They were certainly less obese,
but still obese.
Then, to keep yourself
at that same level of obese,
you still have
to keep injecting it
at, like, $1,000 a month,
or you’ll go back to your
original level of obese.
But why does
the weight loss plateau,
and what exactly happens
when you do stop the drugs?
I’ll cover both those questions
next.